Inventory of the Kenneth A. Bateman papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Kenneth A. Bateman papers
1946-1968.
85008
Bateman, Kenneth A.
21 manuscript boxes (8.4 linear feet)
Hoover Institution Archives Stanford, California 94305-6010
Correspondence, memoranda, reports, bulletins, and printed matter, relating to educational administration in Germany under Allied occupation, and to subsequent educational policy in West Germany.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1985.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical/Historical Note
American educator; teacher education adviser, Land Hesse, Germany, 1948-1951.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection consists of various materials relating to the German education system, including newspaper clippings, personal correspondence, and numerous pamphlets that outline pre- and post- World War II conditions of the school system in Germany. Foundational aspects of schooling are described, including teacher qualifications, wages, and building layouts. The conditions in Germany are compared to those of the American school system. Examples of student homework and photographs document the education systems of both countries. Bateman's research cumulated with his dissertation.
Arrangement
Arranged as received by subject or physical form but in no apparent order.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the library's online public access catalog.
Education--Germany (West); Educational assistance, American--Germany (West); Germany--History--1945-1990.; Hesse (Germany)
Collection Contents
- File key, June 23 1951 (Box 1)
- Adoption, Weilburg, Nov 1948-June 1950 (Box 1)
- Administrative memos, Oct 1948-June 1950 (Box 1)
- American schools: buildings, etc., May 1948 (Box 1)
- Amtsblatt translations, teacher training law, June 1948-May 1951 (Box 1)
- Administration general, April 1949-January 1951 (Box 1)
- Adoptions, donations, and parcels, Dec 1948-June 1949 (Box 1)
- Amerika-HAUS, 1950 (Box 1)
- Art conference, April-May 1948 (Box 1)
- Art education, May-Sep 1948 (Box 1)
- Buildings and education, 1949-1950 (Box 1)
- Associations and organizations, Oct-Nov 1950 (Box 1)
- Basic Principles for the Democracy of Education in Germany, undated (Box 1)
- Book lists, personal, 29 June 1949 (Box 1)
- Child guidance, 31 October 1949 (Box 1)
- Calendar, 1950-1951 (Box 1)
- Adoption, Jugenheim, June 1948-March 1950 (Box 1)
- Articles, 1949-1950 (Box 1)
- High Commission for Occupied Germany (HICOG) teacher education section meetings, May-Sep 1948 (Box 2)
- Comparative education, 22 September 1950 (Box 2)
- Prescott conference, Weilburg, May 1948 (Box 2)
- Citizenship training, Nov 1946, Jan 1947 (Box 2)
- German conferences, April-June 1950 (Box 2)
- Conferences, Nov 1, 1950 (Box 2)
- Institute for Child Study, Aug 1949-Nov 1950 (Box 2)
- American conferences, 21 October 1949 (Box 2)
- Heidelberg workshop, August 1950 (Box 2)
- Interviews, Feb 1949-March 1951 (Box 2)
- Joint conferences, April 1948-March 1950 (Box 2)
- Schwalbach conferences, July 1949-March 1950 (Box 2)
- Staff meeting, July 1948-August 1950 (Box 2)
- Constitution of Land Hessen, December 1946 (Box 2)
- Federal constitution, Sep 1949-1950 (Box 2)
- Commission on Occupied Areas, November 1950 (Box 2)
- Correspondence with other countries and Laender, Nov 1948-June 1951 (Box 2)
- Correspondence with other American authorities, Sep-Nov 1950 (Box 2)
- Correspondence with US, personal, 1949-1951 (Box 2)
- Correspondence, 1948-1951 (Box 2)
- Correspondence with Germans, miscellaneous, July 1948-Jan 1966 (Box 2)
- Correspondence with German government ministries, April 1948-Nov 1950 (Box 2)
- Final reports, Nov 1948-May 1949 (Box 3)
- White House conference, 1950 (Box 3)
- Consultants, 1949-1950 (Box 3)
- International Workshop in Social Studies, 1948-1950 (Box 3)
- New education fellowship, Sep 1950-June 1951 (Box 3)
- Consultant reports, June-Sep 1950 (Box 3)
- Consultant reports, 1949 (Box 3)
- Elementary education, September 1949 (Box 4)
- Consultants, German, Sep 1948-Jan 1949 (Box 4)
- Consultants, US, March-June 1949 (Box 4)
- Student exchanges, April-June 1949 (Box 4)
- Dollar and Deutsche Mark projects, Sep-Oct 1950 (Box 4)
- Extra curricular activities, 9 July 1950 (Box 4)
- Daily bulletin, 1950-Feb1951 (Box 4)
- Dependent achools, 1950-Feb1951 (Box 4)
- Education Service Counter, October 1949 (Box 4)
- Policies: Military Government titles, 23 and 24, Nov-Dec 1948 (Box 4)
- Title 8, Sep 1949-1950 (Box 4)
- Consultants, FY 1949, Oct-Dec 1948 (Box 4)
- Educational guidance, Jan-Feb 1949 (Box 4)
- Education Service Centers, April 1949-July 1950 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, personal, prior to Feb 1948 (Box 4)
- Correspondence, US officials, May 1948-June 1951 (Box 4)
- Consultants, German, February 1950 (Box 4)
- Consultants, European, Nov 1948-June 1949 (Box 4)
- Consultants, German, 1950 (Box 4)
- Cultural exchange, 1949-Aug 1950 (Box 4)
- Student applications, July 1950 (Box 4)
- Exchange staff meetings, April-June 1952 (Box 4)
- Student exchanges, undated (Box 4)
- Student applications, Aug 1949-Jan 1950 (Box 4)
- Finance, Sep 1948-Feb 1949 (Box 4)
- German youth program, 18 September 1950 (Box 4)
- Bill Wrinkles, Die Monatliche Gazette, Oct 1951-April 1952 (Box 4)
- German lessons, undated (Box 4)
- GAI Newsletter, July-Aug 1950 (Box 4)
- Group discussion materials, March 1949-July 1947 (Box 4)
- Possible candidates for scholarships and fellowships, June-Aug 1948 (Box 4)
- Historical reports, no. I, April 1946-1950 (Box 4)
- Hans Schwalbach, July 1950 (Box 4)
- German political scene, 1949 (Box 4)
- File key, July 1950 (Box 5)
- History, education, general, 14 September 1950 (Box 5)
- History and information on German education, June 1948 (Box 5)
- Inservice teacher education, Aug 1949-April 1951 (Box 5)
- Home and family life education, July 1949 (Box 5)
- Infant and junior education, 1948-1949 (Box 5)
- Inservice teacher education, Rheinhardwaldschule, September 1950 (Box 5)
- Inservice training of teachers, undated (Box 5)
- Institut fuer Sozialarbeit und Erziehungshilfe, May-July 1950 (Box 5)
- Instruction material, July-Aug 1948 (Box 5)
- Invitations, 1950-1951 (Box 5)
- Institute of World Affairs, Oct 1949-Dec 1950 (Box 5)
- Jena Plan: Peter Peterson, Feb 1949-April 1950 (Box 5)
- Japan: memorandum for voluntary agents, 30 November 1950 (Box 5)
- Language education, Oct 1948-May 1949 (Box 5)
- Michigan Department of Public Instruction, 1950 (Box 5)
- Ministerial policies, April 1948-June 1951 (Box 5)
- Historical reports, no. IV, Nov 1945-Aug 1948 (Box 5)
- Historical reports, no. II, Sep 1945-June 1946 (Box 5)
- Peter Peterson, 1923-Dec 1950 (Box 5)
- Operations report, February 1949 (Box 5)
- Paedagogische Arbeisstaetten, 1949-May 1952 (Box 6)
- Pestalozzi, Frobl, Walter Asmus, December 1950 (Box 6)
- Students, 4 January 1949 (Box 6)
- Moralische Aufraestung, 1950 (Box 6)
- Organization of Office of the Land Commissioner for Hesse table of organizations, figure 3, undated (Box 6)
- Newspaper abstracts, May 1949-Aug 1950 (Box 6)
- Odenwald Schule, 1957 (Box 6)
- Monthly reports, April 1948-April 1951 (Box 6)
- HICOG and MG Policies, Oct 1949-Sep 1950 (Box 6)
- Paedagogisches Institut Jugenheim, May 1948-June 1951 (Box 6)
- Paedagogische Institut Darmstadt Jugenheim, 1945-1951 (Box 6)
- Paedagogische Ausbildungs, Lehrgang, Dassel, Borken, 1945-1951 (Box 6)
- Paedagogisches Institut Weilburg, undated (Box 6)
- Parent school cooperation, Nov 1948-Nov 1949 (Box 6)
- Other education officers, May 1948-Aug 1950 (Box 6)
- Parent education, Jugenheim, April-June 1949 (Box 6)
- Jugenheim curricula, June 1948-Dec 1949 (Box 6)
- Parent education Finance, May 1949-Aug 1950 (Box 6)
- Parent education, Kassel, March-June 1948 (Box 6)
- Parent education Finance, Fulda, June-Sep 1949 (Box 6)
- Parent education Finance, Jugenheim, Aug-Dec 1949 (Box 6)
- Parent education Finance, Kassel, Aug 1949-June 1950 (Box 6)
- Parent education Finance, Weilburg, Aug 1949-Oct 1950 (Box 6)
- Parent education, May 1948-Nov 1949 (Box 6)
- Personnel and jobs, Dec 1948-June 1951 (Box 6)
- Memos, miscellaneous, Aug 1948-June 1951 (Box 6)
- Directives, Dec 1947-March 1951 (Box 7)
- Consultant reports, 31 August 1950 (Box 7)
- Working folder, 1952 (Box 7)
- Consultants, 1951 (Box 7)
- Curriculum, 1948 (Box 7)
- Historical reports, no. III, Sep 1945-March 1950 (Box 7)
- Landesschulbeirat fuer Hessen, June-Sep 1949 (Box 7)
- "Home Economics in Urban Areas,", June 1950-January 1951 (Box 7)
- Christmas committee, June 10-Aug 31, 1950 (Box 7)
- Education, general, 1946-1950 (Box 7)
- Institut fuer Jugenkunde, Dec 1947-Aug 1949 (Box 8)
- Faculty, June 1941-1950 (Box 8)
- Physical education, August 1949 (Box 8)
- Bibliographies, March 1949 (Box 8)
- Lehrer Bildung plan, 22 March 1951 (Box 8)
- Property control, 23 September 1949 (Box 8)
- Psychology of learning and educational method, May 1950- (Box 8)
- Commission for Youth Publications, 29 July 1948 (Box 8)
- German publications, April 1948-March 1949 (Box 8)
- News of the week, April 1949-March 1950 (Box 8)
- Teacher newspapers, February 1951 (Box 8)
- Students' and youth publications and newspapers, April 1949-Jan 1950 (Box 8)
- Radio education, 31 August 1950 (Box 8)
- Radio Distribution Commission, October 1947 (Box 8)
- Roberts Rules of Order, in German, undated (Box 8)
- Sechsjaehrige Grundschule, 26 January 1949 (Box 8)
- School Administration Law of Hessen, 10 July 1953 (Box 8)
- Reichsbuergergesetz (Reich Citizenship Law), 15 September 1935 (Box 8)
- Hessian laws, 1948 (Box 8)
- School legislation, Aug-Sep 1950 (Box 8)
- School reform, April 1948-Feb 1951 (Box 8)
- School reform in other Laender, Aug 1950-June 1951 (Box 8)
- Social science, April-Aug 1949 (Box 8)
- Social welfare workers, 1949-1950 (Box 8)
- Special education, 1945-Sep 1948 (Box 8)
- Title 8 and policy directive PA, 28 July 1950 (Box 9)
- Speeches, Dec 1949-March 1950 (Box 9)
- PF teacher education draft law, Sep-Oct 1949 (Box 9)
- Germany: old Stars and Stripes, 1948-1949 (Box 9)
- Tests, April 1949-May 1950 (Box 9)
- Association of Colleges for Teacher Education, 3 March 1951 (Box 9)
- Geist und Forme in der neuen Lehrerbildung, undated (Box 9)
- Teacher education, general, March-Oct 1948 (Box 9)
- Association of Western German Colleges, Feb-May 1951 (Box 9)
- American Association of Colleges for Teacher Education (AACTE), October 1948 (Box 9)
- Association of Teachers Colleges in Western Germany, May-June 1951 (Box 9)
- Translations, undated (Box 9)
- Typed and mimeographed material, June 1951 (Box 9)
- Workshops, June 1948-October 1949 (Box 9)
- Teacher mailing list, undated (Box 9)
- Vocational teacher training, Aug 1948-June 1951 (Box 9)
- Kindergarten and youth leader training, September 1950 (Box 9)
- Textbooks, Oct-Dec 1949 (Box 9)
- Special and institutional schools, March 1948-April 1949 (Box 9)
- Specialized foreign service personnel exchange plan, April 30, 1951 (Box 9)
- Teacher associations, Dec 3, 1947-April 22, 1949 (Box 9)
- Curricular Standards for Teacher Education State Department, New Jersey, undated (Box 9)
- Teacher examination, June 1947-1948 (Box 9)
- Teacher supply data, Feb 1948-April 1950 (Box 9)
- Statistics, prior to 1933-March 1951 (Box 10)
- Monthly reports, Dec 1950-May 1951 (Box 10)
- Speeches and discussion material, March-May 1949 (Box 10)
- School buildings, 1950 (Box 10)
- Secondary school teacher training, September 1948 (Box 10)
- Photographs, labelled, 1946-1949 (Box 10)
- Neilburg Paedagogisches Institut, undated (Box 10)
- Photographs, US Army, 1946 (Box 10)
- German teacher group returning from the US, 1953-1954 (Box 10)
- International youth working conference, April 2-10, 1951 (Box 10)
- Photographs of German events in Hessen, 1946 (Box 10)
- School for blind children, Friedberg, Land Hessen, undated (Box 10)
- Reinhardswaldschule, inservice teacher education residential center, April 1951 (Box 10)
- US dependent school: high school students, 1946 (Box 10)
- Wiesbaden dependent school, Feb 1, 1951 (Box 10)
- Photographs, American schools, April 5, 1948 (Box 10)
- Washington Post, Dec 26, 1954 (Box 10)
- Teacher education law, Dec 1948-Dec 1949 (Box 10)
- Reorientation program, June 1949-April 1950 (Box 10)
- Waldorf schools, undated (Box 11)
- Gesamt und Einheitsschule, March 1965-1967 (Box 11)
- "Educational Leadership" article and materials, 1964-1968 (Box 11)
- Democratizing education, undated (Box 11)
- Vocational education, March 1965-1967 (Box 11)
- Driver's education, March 1966 (Box 11)
- General, Sep 1965-Jan 1966 (Box 11)
- Educational leadership, March 1967-May 1968 (Box 11)
- Newspaper clippings, Jan-Sep 1965 (Box 11)
- Newspaper clippings, May 1964-Jan 1966 (Box 11)
- German parliament, Sep 23, 1964 (Box 11)
- Newspaper clippings, 1964-1965 (Box 11)
- Newspaper clippings, 1964-1966 (Box 11)
- Paedagogisches Institut Weilburg, June 1948-June 1951 (Box 11)
- Paedagogischer Ausbildungslehrgang Frankfurt/Maine, Dec 1948 (Box 11)
- Teacher training institutions, Jan 1951 (Box 11)
- Fulda-Kassel situation information, undated (Box 11)
- Paedagogischer Ausbildungslehrgang Kassel, Aug 1949-Fep 1950 (Box 11)
- Paedagogischer Ausbilduugslehrgang FULDA, Sep 1948-Aug 1949 (Box 11)
- Correspondence, US officials, Oct 1962-June 1966 (Box 11)
- Universities, Aug 1949 (Box 11)
- Volksschullehrausbildung, elementary school teacher training, March 1968 (Box 11)
- Printed material, 1954 and undated (Box 12)
- Paedagogische Hausarbeit fuer die Zweite Pruefung zum Gewerbelehramt, undated (Box 12)
- Fache Konzentration, Gesamtunterricht und ganzheitliche Bildung, January 17, 1950 (Box 12)
- Position changes in German education, 1946-1951, Aug 17, 1951 (Box 12)
- Selected Readings on The Impact of the New Germany, volume two, 1954 (Box 12)
- Education Service Center, 1953 (Box 12)
- Hessische Kreiszahlen, Jan 1951 (Box 12)
- Selected Readings on The Impact of the New Germany, 1954 (Box 12)
- Second annual report of the Education Service Center, March 1, 1951-Feb 29, 1952 (Box 12)
- "Test Development in Germany,", Feb 1952 (Box 13)
- "Change of Attitudes in German Exchanges,", Nov 17, 1950 (Box 13)
- US Resident Officers conference, December 12-13, 1949 (Box 13)
- News brochures, miscellaneous, Jan 1951-Dec 1957 (Box 13)
- "Office of Public Affairs: Report for November 1950,", Nov 1950 (Box 13)
- US Resident Officers conference, Dec 12-13, 1949 (Box 13)
- Das Kind, Nov 1949-Jan 1951 (Box 13)
- Hessische Lehrer-Zeitung, April 1949-March 1952 (Box 13)
- Gateway to Germany, 1953 (Box 13)
- Elections and political parties in Germany, 1945-1952 (Box 13)
- Community action team, 1953 (Box 14)
- Teacher education in Hesse, Dec 1948-Aug 1949 (Box 14)
- Informational reports, 1953 (Box 14)
- Schuldorf Bergstrasse school village, 1953 (Box 14)
- Reports, memoranda, and correspondence, 1951 (Box 14)
- Reports, memoranda, and correspondence, 1952 (Box 14)
- Pre-opening conference, 1954 (Box 14)
- Schuldorf Bergstrasse press book, undated (Box 14)
- Hesse, 1950 (Box 14)
- Darmstadt, Germany, undated (Box 14)
- Schuldorf Bergstrasse prepared for the official opening ceremonies, 1954 (Box 14)
- Gemeintag article by Wink, with translations, 1956 (Box 14)
- Bodenman, 1957-1958 (Box 14)
- Becker, 1957-1958 (Box 14)
- Keske, 1957-1958 (Box 14)
- Berger, 1957-1958 (Box 14)
- Geissler, 1957-1958 (Box 14)
- Bateman, 1955 (Box 14)
- Schuldorf Bergstrasse clippings, April 1954 (Box 14)
- Schuldorf Bergstrasse reports and correspondence, 1954 (Box 14)
- Schuldorf Bergstrasse article, undated (Box 14)
- Schuldorf Bergstrasse school village, Jan-March 1956 (Box 14)
- Germany's parliament in action, Sep 1949-1950 (Box 15)
- Die Rolenfibel, 1949 (Box 15)
- Lemberg, 1957-1958 (Box 15)
- Hilker, Oct 1957-Jan 1958 (Box 15)
- Ploetz, 1957-1958 (Box 15)
- Neunzerling, 1957-1958 (Box 15)
- Karlsson, Oct 1957-Jan 1958 (Box 15)
- Staender, Nov 1957-Jan 1958 (Box 15)
- Trost, 1957-1958 (Box 15)
- Wittig, Oct 1957-Nov 1959 (Box 15)
- Plewe, Jan 16, 1958 (Box 15)
- Master letters, 1958 (Box 15)
- Wink, Oct 1957-Nov 1959 (Box 15)
- Bratu, Jan 1958 (Box 15)
- Biesanz, March 14, 1959 (Box 15)
- Klotsches report, July 2, 1955 (Box 15)
- John Steiners report, July 1945-Aug 1950 (Box 15)
- Report of Jenson and Weil, May 6, 1954 (Box 15)
- Letter of appreciation, Jan 2, 1962 (Box 15)
- Schuldorf Bergstrasse prepared for the 10th celebration, 1964 (Box 15)
- "Proposal for Doctoral Dissertation,", Oct 31, 1957 (Box 15)
- Schuldorf Bergstrasse photographs, undated (Box 15)
- Schuldorf Bergstrasse clippings, 1964 (Box 15)
- Pamphlets and printed matter, in German and English, 1948-1954 (Box 16-18)
- Mitteilungen und Nachrichten, May 1954-July 1962 (Box 19)
- Heilpaedagogische Blaetter und Mitteilungen, 1949-1951 (Box 20)
- "Proposal for a Doctroal Dissertation Leading to the Degree Doctor of Education,", Oct 31, 1957 (Box 21)